Guide to the Henry Savage Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry Savage papers
1896-1990
OSB MSS 200
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8
(12 boxes)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Maggs Brothers Ltd. on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2015.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Henry Savage (1879-1965)
English author and editor Henry Savage worked for various literary journals in London in the years before World War II. Savage is perhaps best known for his biography of his friend, poet Richard Middleton, Richard Middleton: The man and his work (London: Cecil Palmer, 1922). Other works written by Savage include a novel, How to manage our women (London: Humphrey Toulmin, 1930), an autobiography, The receding shore (London: Grayson & Grayson, 1933) and the poetry collections, Escapes and escapades (London: The Pomegranate Press, 1915), Songs and satires (The Renaissance Press, 1946), and Winged phallus. Works edited by Savage include Richard Middleton's letters to Henry Savage (London: The Mandrake Press, 1929) and The love letters of Henry VIII (London: Allan Wingate, 1949). Savage retired first to Winchelsea, in Sussex, England, then to Capri and Tenerife.
Biographical information taken from Moore, Harry T., "D. H. Lawrence to Henry Savage: An introductory note," The Yale University Library Gazette 34, 1 (July 1959).
Scope and Contents
The Henry Savage papers consists of writings, correspondence, and other papers relating to English author and editor Henry Savage. Writings feature printed versions of shorter works by Savage and several drafts. Printed versions of essays and reviews appear to have been assembled for possible publication as a collection or selection of writings. Other writings by Savage include drafts of a late work of reminiscences, "Promenade picaresque," and page proofs for a work of verse entitled Winged phallus.
Series II. Correspondence includes correspondence with authors, booksellers, publishers, literary scholars, friends, and family. The Henry Savage Correspondence includes all incoming and outgoing letters between Savage and others. There are incoming letters from Armin Arnold, William Heinemann Ltd., René MacColl, Burns Singer, Wilfrid C. Thorley, and Colin Wilson, and outgoing letters to "Bess" Greville, Guy Rayne Savage (Henry's son), and Valentine Watts. Some letters to and from Guy Rayne Savage document his service as executor of his father's literary estate. Additional correspondents include Bertram Rota Ltd. and E. L. McAdam.
Other Papers contains clippings, journals, photographs, printed material, and personal papers. The series features a run of 26 handwritten journals spanning three full decades from 1933 to 1963. A photograph album and photographs contain images of Savage, family, and unidentified others.
Collection material is chiefly in English; with some materials in Spanish.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Writings, 1911-1964. II. Correspondence, 1896-1990. III. Other Papers, 1900-1980.
Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Criticism -- 20th century.; Poets, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Photographic prints; Authors -- England -- 20th Century; Poets -- England; Arnold, Armin; Greville, Bess; McAdam, E. L. (Edward Lippincott), 1905-1969; MacColl, René; Savage, Guy Rayne; Savage, Henry; Singer, Burns; Thorley, Wilfrid C. (Wilfrid Charles), 1978-; Watts, Valentine; Wilson, Colin, 1931-2013; Bertram Rota Ltd; Heinemann (Firm)
- Writings, 1911-1964; 1920-1925; 2.54; (4 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Essays and Reviews, Other Writings, and Writings of Others.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Writings, features printed versions of shorter works by Savage and several drafts. Printed versions of "essays and reviews" appear to have been assembled for possible publication as a collection or selection of writings. The writings, which date chiefly from the early 1920s, appear in three separate publications, Book notes illustrated, Bookman's journal, and The new witness. These writings, now arranged alphabetically by title, are attributed to Savage and to various pseudonyms. Pseudonyms include Adrian Harley, Anthony Scrope, and Worthington Cadogan. Many of the titles published under a pseudonym are initialed, "HS".
  Other writings by Savage include drafts of a late work of reminiscences, "Promenade picaresque," a marked copy of Songs and satires, and page proofs for a work of verse entitled Winged phallus.
  - Essays and Reviews
    - "An afternoon at Sotheby's auction room," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Andrew Marvell, poet," printed version, Bookman's journal (2 copies), 1921 April 1 (Box 1)
    - "The antiquary's cabinet," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The apotheosis of Joanna Southcott," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Aristocrats in exile: Behind the scenes of a revolution," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "An Artemis in trousers," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Back to George Eliot," printed version, Book notes illustrated (3 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Beckford of Fonthill: Author, collector, millionaire and eccentric," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Books and browsings," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1921 June 24 (Box 1)
    - "Books and the man: Grant Richards," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 October 1 (Box 1)
    - "Booksellers as authors," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), 1924 (Box 1)
    - "Byron," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), 1924 (Box 1)
    - "Catalogue review: Francis Edwards," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 November 19 (Box 1)
    - "A chance for millionaires," printed version Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "A chance for the philistines," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 September 3 (Box 1)
    - "Charles Lamb and the musical glasses," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 August 13 (Box 2)
      Includes "Fairy gold: A word with sir J. M. Barrie"
    - "Christmas in December," printed version, undated (Box 1)
    - "Christmas in the 'Eighties," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "A city of spells: Some impressions of Oxford," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1921 May 13 (Box 1)
    - "A city of spells: Some impressions of Oxford," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "A cockney in Cornwall," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "Coloured cats and stray clouds," printed version, The new witness, 1922 May 12 (Box 1)
    - "Coloured cats and stray clouds," printed version, The new witness, [1922 May 12] (Box 2)
    - "Conrad chez lui," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1921 March 11 (Box 1)
    - "Cooings in the dove-coterie," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 May 7 (Box 1)
    - "Creative effort," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Curiosities of rhyming slang," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "D'Israeli's 'miscellanies of literature'," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "E. V. Lucas," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "An Elizabethan tercentenary," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), 1925 (Box 1)
    - "A famous bookbindery," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The first picaresque novel: Petronius and 'The Satyricon'," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Francis Thompson as seen by a Hindu," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The gas purrs," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1921 January 7 (Box 1)
    - "The gas purrs," printed version, [ Bookman's journal ], [1921 January 7] (Box 2)
    - "Hapless Marie Antoinette: The most tragic figure of the French Revolution," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Henry James at Rye," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Hodgsons: London's famous book auctioneers," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The impudence of George Moore: His attack on Thomas Hardy," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Is 'Ulysses' a creation? Hugh Walpole overlooks a lady," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Isaac d'Israeli's 'Curiosities of literature'," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Juvenilia: The library of Mr. C. J. Owen," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "Lady Macbeth in pigtails," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "A lament for Bohemia," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The laureateship," printed version, undated (Box 2)
      Includes "Back to Maecenas: The patronage of letters"
    - "Life and Joseph Conrad," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Life and letters," printed version, undated (Box 1)
    - "The literary portrait gallery," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The London stage in 1840," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "The lucky Opal," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 September 17 (Box 1)
    - "The lunatic litterateur: A remarkable book by a deranged lady," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "The man in the iron mask," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "A memory of Cassel," printed version, undated (Box 1)
    - "Men and matters," printed versions, Bookman's journal, 1920 (Box 1)
    - "Modern verse and some misgivings," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1921 July 1 (Box 1)
    - "The moral of the 'Nineties," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The most fascinating villain in literature," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The mystery of Richard Savage," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Napoleon as a human being: Side lights from a catalogue of letters," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "A neglected poet," printed version, Bookman's journal, undated (Box 1)
    - "New light on Colonel Lawrence of Arabia," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "A new sentimental journey," printed versions, Bookman's journal, 1920 (Box 1)
    - "Notes on modern first editions," printed versions, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Notes on private collections: Some books and mss. in the library of Dr. A. T. Rake," printed version, Bookman's journal, undated (Box 2)
    - "An old album: A charming ghost of a bygone day," printed version, Book notes illustrated (3 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "An old album," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 October 22 (Box 2)
    - "The palace of pleasure," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Paris revisited," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "The passing of Bohemia," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "The passion for antiques," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Passion in poetry," printed versions, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Piccadilly," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "The poetry of Thomas Ashe: A forgotten Victorian," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Poor Robin's almanack: A diverting seventeenth century production," printed versions, Book notes illustrated (3 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "The psychology of ghost fiction," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "A quiet tune," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 June 4 (Box 1)
    - "Rebecca West," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The receding shore: Pages from the book of my life," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The revolt against rhyme: A Milton preface," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "The roaring 'Forties," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "Robert Herrick," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Sentimental song," printed version, undated (Box 2)
      Includes "Books and browsings," "Poetasters and the spring," and "The legions of oblivion"
    - "Shakespeare and some musical glasses: Stories from a forgotten volume of theatrical memoirs," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "The Shakespeare mystery: New light on Mr. W. H.," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "A Shelley discovery," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Sherwood Anderson meets the policeman: Questions raised by a recent trial," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Slavery and freedom," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 May 21 (Box 1)
    - "Sphinx and basilisk," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 July 30 (Box 1)
    - "The spirit of the age," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "Stories of the old playhouse," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Stories of the old playhouses," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1920 November 26 (Box 2)
    - "A sub-acid test for a queen," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1921 April 22 (Box 1)
    - "T. W. H. Crosland, 1865-1924: The passing of an English poet," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 1)
    - "Tattered passions," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1921 February 18 (Box 1)
    - "Thomas Campion and a fair lady," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 1)
    - "Thomas Campion and his 'dark lady'," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "Thomas Lodge," printed version, Book notes illustrated, 1925 April (Box 3)
    - "Thomas Lovell Beddoes, poet of the macabre," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 3)
    - "The thousand nights and one night," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 3)
    - "The three Peter Bells," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "The tragedy of Anatole France," printed version, Book notes illustrated (3 copies), undated (Box 3)
    - "Tribute to Balbus: An archaeological affair," printed version, Bookman's journal (2 copies), 1921 February 11 (Box 3)
    - "The unpublished part of 'De profundis': New light on Oscar Wilde's prison document," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 3)
    - "Variations on a stale subject," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "Walter de la Mare: A great poet and novelist," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 3)
    - "We old Victorians," printed version, The new witness, 1922 June 23 (Box 3)
    - "We old Victorians," printed version, The new witness, 1922 June 23 (Box 2)
    - "What the public wants: Charlie Chaplin and the public demand," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 3)
    - "William Blake: Poet, seer, and prophet," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 3)
    - "William Ernest Henley," printed version, Bookman's journal, 1921 June 10 (Box 2)
    - "Willow and titwillow," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "The wing of friendship: With some remarks on Keats, Shelley and Byron," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "A wonder book of beasts," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 3)
    - "A wonder book of beasts," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - "Wonders of London Museum," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 3)
    - "The world's longest novel: Eugene Sue and the wandering Jew myth," printed version, Book notes illustrated, undated (Box 3)
    - "The yellow 'Nineties," printed version, Book notes illustrated (2 copies), undated (Box 3)
    - "The youth that knows," printed version, undated (Box 2)
    - Unidentified, 1920, undated (Box 3)
    - Empty case, undated (Box 2)
  - Other Writings
    - "Auden as moralist," printed version, The poetry review, 1952 January (Box 3)
    - "The colour bar: Synopsis of a farce in 3 acts," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 3)
    - "The marquis buys goldfish: A Neapolitan comedy," draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 3)
    - "Nothing is here for tears: Reminiscences," typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 3)
    - "Promenade picaresque," draft, typescript and typescript carbon, corrected, undated; 2 (Box 3)
    - "Promenade picaresque," draft, typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 3)
    - "Promenade picaresque," draft (incomplete), typescript carbon, corrected, undated (Box 3)
    - Richard Middleton's letters, printed version, marked, 1929 (Box 3)
    - Songs and satires, printed version, annotated, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Songs and satires, book cover, circa 1946 (Box 4)
    - Winged phallus: Poems of 'le frittement voluptueux de deux intestins', page proof (2 copies), undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - "Poetry and other writings," drafts, 1911-1964, undated (Box 4)
  - Writings of Others
    - Singer, Burns
      - "The transparent prisoner," revised proof, corrected and signed, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
- Correspondence, 1896-1990; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Henry Savage Correspondence, Guy Rayne Savage Correspondence, and Other Correspondence.
  Series II. includes correspondence with authors, booksellers, publishers, literary scholars, friends, and family. The first subseries, Henry Savage Correspondence, includes all incoming and outgoing letters between Savage and others. There are incoming letters from Armin Arnold, William Heinemann Ltd., René MacColl, Burns Singer, Wilfrid C. Thorley, and Colin Wilson, and outgoing letters to "Bess" Greville, Guy Rayne Savage (Henry's son), and Valentine Watts. There are over one hundred autograph manuscript letters, signed, from Henry to his son, most dating from the mid-1950s onward, after Savage had settled in Tenerife. Letters discuss family, writing and writing projects, books he is reading, trips, and various other aspects of life in Tenerife, such as social activities, his health, and the weather.
  Other letters to and from Guy Rayne Savage comprise the second Correspondence subseries. Many letters post-dating Henry's death in 1965 document Guy Savage's service as executor of his father's literary estate. Additional correspondents include Bertram Rota Ltd. and E. L. McAdam.
  - Henry Savage Correspondence
    - Arnold, Armin, 1958, undated (Box 5)
    - Barrie & Rockliff, 1965 March (Box 5)
    - Charlton, William, no year February 6 (Box 5)
    - Churchill, Winston, 1950 October 25 (Box 5)
    - De Havilland, [?], 1956 January 30 (Box 5)
    - Fields, Grace, 1945-1953, undated (Box 5)
    - Greville, Bess, 1955-1958, undated (Box 5)
    - Heinemann (Firm), 1928 November 9 (Box 5)
    - MacColl, René, 1956 July 1 (Box 5)
    - Merteuil, Madame de, undated (Box 5)
    - Savage, Guy Rayne, 1933-1964, undated; 4 (Box 5)
    - Savage, Henry M., 1952-1958, undated (Box 5)
    - Savage, Yvonne, undated (Box 5)
    - Singer, Burns, 1954 December 7 (Box 5)
    - Thorley, Wilfrid C. (Wilfrid Charles), 1952 (Box 5)
      Includes drafts of poems
    - Wainwright, [Vera?], 1948 September 14 (Box 5)
    - Watts, Valentine, 1955-1959, undated; 2 (Box 5)
    - Wilson, Colin, 1958 October 3 (Box 5)
    - Others and unidentified, 1912-1965, undated (Box 5)
  - Guy Rayne Savage Correspondence
    - Barrie & Rockcliff, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Bertram Rota Ltd., 1965 (Box 5)
    - Evening news, 1965 January 29 (Box 5)
    - Evening standard, 1965 April 29 (Box 5)
    - Lethbridge, Mabel, 1965-1967 (Box 5)
    - McAdam, E. L. (Edward Lippincott), 1965 April (Box 5)
    - McNulty, Robert, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Merwin, Dido, 1980-1981, undated (Box 5)
    - Roderick O'Driscoll & Partners, 1978 August (Box 5)
    - Savage, Henry M., 1964 [July?] 12 (Box 5)
    - Savage, Mrs., 1924, undated (Box 5)
    - Wigram & Co., 1965 (Box 5)
    - Wilson, Colin, 1965 April (Box 5)
    - Others, 1937-1990, undated (Box 5)
    - "Condolences", 1980 (Box 5)
  - Other Correspondence
    - Bulteel, Christopher H. to Tansley Witt & Co., undated (Box 6)
    - [Greville?], Bess to "Mamma", 1896 October 16 (Box 6)
    - Lowe, Olive to Dr. Horder, no year May 24 (Box 6)
    - Ridley, Cathe[y?] H. to unidentified, 1980 May 2 (Box 6)
    - Savage, Henry M. to "grandma", 1957-1958, undated (Box 6)
    - Savage, Henry M. with others, 1988-1990, undated (Box 6)
    - Silkin, Rosa A. to Dr. Horder, 1980 April 22 (Box 6)
    - ----, "Madeleine" to [Valentine Watts], 1945 April 20
    - ----, "Marthe" to Yvonne Savage, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
    - ----, "Stacey" to Henry [M. Savage?], undated (Box 6)
    - ----, "Sue" to Henry M. Savage, 1961 October 1 (Box 6)
    - Unidentified, 1960-1965, undated (Box 6)
- Other Papers, 1900-1980; 4.63; (6 boxes)
  Arranged alhabetically by material type and heading.
  Series III. contains clippings, journals, photographs, printed material, and additional personal papers. The series features a run of 26 handwritten journals spanning three full decades from 1933 to 1963. A photograph album and loose photographs contain images of Savage, family, and unidentified others. Most photographs in the collection show Savage as an older man, and would appear to date from the mid-1950s forward.
  - Address book, circa 1961-1964, undated (Box 6)
  - "Agenda for the Twenty First Meeting of the Governors...", undated (Box 6)
  - Baptismal record for Henry Louis Savage, 1914 April 23 (Box 6)
  - Biographical sketch of Henry Savage, undated (Box 6)
  - Clippings, 1952-1962, undated (Box 6)
  - Clipping, 1959 April 17 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Clippings removed from address book, 1960-1963, undated (Box 6)
  - Clippings removed from Richard Middleton's Letters (London: Mandrake, 1929), 1900-1955, undated (Box 6)
  - Clippings removed from Richard Middleton's Letters (London: Mandrake, 1929), 1922-1951 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Empty envelope, undated (Box 6)
  - Empty folders, undated; 3 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Financial records, 1954-1961, undated (Box 6)
  - Insurance policy proposal, 1955 October 28 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Journals, 1933-1945; 3 (Box 6)
  - Journals, 1945-1952; 5 (Box 7)
  - Journals, 1952-1957; 11 (Box 8)
  - Journals, 1957-1958; 3 (Box 9)
  - Material removed from journal (1958), 1958 June 13 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Journal, 1959; 2 (Box 9)
  - Material removed from journal (1959), undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Journals, 1959-1962; 3 (Box 9)
  - Clippings removed from journal (1962), 1962-1963 (Box 12 (Oversize))
  - Journals, 1963, undated; 2 (Box 10)
  - Last will and testament of Henry Savage, undated (Box 10)
  - List of addresses, 1979 November 1 (Box 10)
  - Manuscript fragments, undated (Box 10)
  - Manuscript fragments removed from address book, undated (Box 10)
  - "A month by month plan of action for the viticulturist with a vinery", 1978, undated (Box 10)
  - Negatives removed from address book, undated (Box 10)
  - "Notes on London area group leaders meeting", 1980 February 19 (Box 10)
  - Photograph album, 1941-1958, undated (Box 11)
  - Photographs, 1941-1943, undated (Box 10)
  - Photographs removed from address book, 1963, undated (Box 10)
  - Prescription removed from address book, 1964 April 16 (Box 10)
  - Printed ephemera, 1959, undated (Box 10)